[Music]
hello everybody it is so nice to be back
with you all
good evening and good day i hope you're
doing well
so for those of you who don't know i was
a little unwell last week i was down
with the virus i thought it was covered
but then i later taste tested coved
negative
and yet it was a very nasty virus so i
was bedridden for
a week
and i am better now
i am recovering
the illness is over but i am yet to
recover my strength so it's i'm working
on it but i'm better much better
so i would like to thank you all for all
your wishes
and for your messages of support i'm
very honored thank you very much very
grateful
thank you very much to all of you who
supported me
so let's see who all is there
tonight with us
i can see rp
to him
saurabh
and so many more people
it's great to see you all it's great to
see you all thank you so much for being
here with us
and i would also like to thank all of
you who have been supporting this
channel becoming members or supporting
via paypal or other means thank you very
much to all of you
i really appreciate your support
so let us begin today's session uh i am
going to keep it i'm going to cap
today's session at around 1 hour because
i'm still not strong enough
so so let's get going
there is no specific topic of today's
discussion ask me anything you would
like to ask me and i will answer
so that's what we will do today
so what do we have what questions do we
have you have questions ask me the
questions
satoru gojo says what was your
experience okay there are three
questions here
firstly what was my experience in the
field of mathematics i think mathematics
is a fantastic field
sometimes one is tempted to just abandon
physics and get right into pure
mathematics because it is a field of
great beauty and truth
and i suppose it is a little less
controversial than physics
maybe i'm wrong maybe there is enough
controversy in mathematics as well but
it's a it's a very nice field it is a
field that is worth pursuing on its own
so yeah i really enjoy mathematics it's
great
sometimes i am tempted to go into pure
mathematics and forget about physics you
know
uh question number two why did i leave
sangam talks talks when was i ever with
sangam talks
i have done a couple of invited
talks with sangam talks
the experience has always been very good
very nice people very
very good platform they have been doing
a very good job for many years
inviting people from
various disparate fields and and
presenting that knowledge on one single
platform it's a very good platform i
have always enjoyed working with them
and i may work with them again in the
future
so i have never left sangam talks i was
never with sangam talks i did not ever
work with them but
i have as you know uh done a couple of
talks with them and i'm
of course certainly open to doing such
talks again in the future
question number three what is wave
particle duality wave particle duality
is one of the cornerstone concepts in
quantum mechanics
in which a particle
has a dual nature it is a particle as
well as a wave at the same time so a
photon behaves like a wave it also
behaves like a particle depending on the
context the same goes for electrons and
all other
quantum mechanical particles so that is
wave particle duality
okay what other questions do we have
what other questions do we have uh
anirban says how to become an astronomer
in india
i don't think there is much scope in
astronomy in india because first of all
we don't have
many facilities for
the pursuit of astronomy
in this country there are a couple of
reasonably okay telescopes i think there
is a good telescope somewhere in ladakh
where the night sky is quite dark
and maybe one or two other telescopes so
that's all you have for for
observational astronomy
so i think there is not much scope for
pursuing astronomy as a career or as a
field of research in india thus far
india has always lagged behind in the
sciences because there is so
so little infrastructure and so few
facilities
but i am sure there are lots of
opportunities outside of india
especially in the developed world in
europe and
in the americas
so how do you become an astronomer you
you
you have to
get yourself
a bachelor's degree and a master's
degree in physics i'm not sure
if many colleges or universities offer
astronomy as
the specialization but as long as you
have a degree in physics you can
certainly
pursue
astronomy
so the basic prerequisite the minimum
prerequisite is to have a degree at
least a bachelor's degree in physics
ideally a master's degree and then you
can go for a phd or something like that
in astronomy maybe if not in india if
then somewhere else so that's how you
that is the typical standard career path
for pursuing
astronomy
what was that okay here it is so joy
kumar gosh asks why were buddhists
executed in ancient india by indian
rulers
i am not aware of any buddhists being
executed in india by ancient rulers
do you have any specific examples
and also we have to remember that
if one or two incidents like that happen
somewhere it doesn't mean it was the
rule the exception is not the rule as
far as i can recall i cannot remember
any such
incidents of any persecution of
buddhists by indian rulers there was a
time when
almost the entirety of india was
essentially buddhist
because both the dharma was the
prevalent uh
flavor
of culture that was
that was
in vogue in india for a very long period
of time during the mauryan era during
the gup of during the kushan era etc
it is only during the time of
shankaracharya that the other flavors of
dharma
began to revive
but as far as i know there have been
there have been absolutely no
significant
instances of persecution of buddhists
by indian rulers because the statement
you have put here makes it look like it
was a widespread kind of practice which
is which is not correct
yes i was expecting a question about a
uk us so the question is
is a uk us the latest organization
between between the us uk and the
aussies a replacement for the quad and
what does it mean for india so this
trilateral
uh forum
or or alliance
a uk us
is not a replacement for the quad it is
a subgrouping of the five eyes
confederation
so there is something called the five
eyes five eyes grouping
it is an alliance of the
english-speaking nations
essentially the us
canada uk australia and new zealand
these are the five
english-speaking anglo-saxon nations
so the americans trust their own people
more than anybody else and they have
this grouping called the five eyes
so auk us is a subset of five eyes
it is
a military alliance of the united states
australia and the uk and its sole
objective is to counter china and
chinese expansionism especially in the
indo-pacific region
so what happened was that the
australians had this contract with the
french
under which they would
acquire they were they would have
acquired 12
french
diesel electric submarines for about i
don't know 60 billion dollars something
like that
right
and
the americans made the australians
cancel this agreement
and in exchange the americans are going
to sell the australians nuclear
submarines
so that is why this entire thing is in
the news a uk us and the french are very
upset about this about this development
they have recalled their ambassador to
the us and to australia
but the australians have done what the
americans told them maybe it is for the
best for them because diesel-electric
submarines aren't
that great
for
long-term
maritime
deterrence deterrence purposes
especially when the chinese do have a
few nuclear submarines so it is
i think best for the australians and for
this grouping
that the australians would have
would were to buy
american nuclear submarines so it makes
sense for them and that's why they have
gone for it
now so this is not a replacement for the
quad the quad is not a military alliance
it is a multi-purpose alliance in in
which the military element is
is uh
not very prominent
so
a uk us is not a replacement for the
quad it is something that will augment
the quad to a certain extent
so what does it mean for india it
doesn't
change much for india maybe it does give
india
strategic opportunities
to
to cooperate
with the french more closely than we
already are india and france have
a de facto strategic
partnership
which is it is a very close partnership
there is a significant military element
to it
india has been buying french submarines
french fighter aircraft the rafale
aircraft and there are certain other
elements of cooperation as well that may
not be very well known or very well
publicized
so it gives india the opportunity to to
to
to work even more closely with the
french
but it doesn't
harm india in any way it doesn't mean
that india has been left out in some way
by the americans or by the australians
or anything
the americans australians
and the british have always been a very
tight-knit group
the americans trust their own people
significantly more than they trust the
indians or the japanese so it doesn't
really change a lot for india
india's uh
india's relationship with the americans
or the australians won't change much
because of this development
okay some more questions
damanja sharma asks mr gandhi's role in
embracing the mobile genocide my take on
the mobile genocide it is something that
happened exactly 100 years ago in the
malabar region kerala
it was a full-blown rebellion against
by the by the mauplas
the converted muslims in kerala it was
definitely a genocide and mr gandhi was
well
he kind of condoned it
he did not
yeah you could say he embraced it so he
did not condemn what was happening
mr gandhi did not go on a fast until
death
to induce the
the the rioters to stop rioting and
massacring people he did nothing of that
sort
so it is one of the most infamous uh
episodes
of history where as far as it
as far as mr gandhi is concerned it
completely exposed his double standards
he had a certain set of standards for
for hindus and it's a another set of
standards for the british and yet one
one more set of standards for
the people who followed foreign
religions in india so mr gandhi was a
proper hypocrite and this uh
and what he did during the mobile
genocide completely bears this out it
totally exposes him
we one just has to one just needs to
look up what he wrote during those days
about the events and it's very clear
what his stand was he was of the opinion
that hindus should just lie down and die
so that's that's how it was so that's
that is unfortunately the truth about mr
gandhi
and these days these
inconvenient facts are all coming out in
the public domain which is a very good
thing
was the caste system introduced the
brahmins to dominate over others the
brahmins were powerless they were people
whose only job was to preserve and
disseminate india's ancient
wisdom
the military do you know where power
comes from what is the meaning of power
nobody has explained power better than
mouth
said that power flows from the barrel of
a gun
in the ancient times when we did not
have guns power flowed from the blade of
a sword
now in india did brahmins wield swords
no
it was the khatriyas
the
the warriors
who held political power in india
right so how how would brahmins dominate
over others
so this is these are all perceptions
that have been created by
the
foreign missionaries over a couple of
centuries and after independence the
same old narratives have been pushed by
india's marxist historians
and this is just going on and today
everybody is so brainwashed that we feel
that yes brahmins are evil brahmanism is
something that exists and brahmins
dominated everybody else and they
introduced caste system and god knows
what else
absolute utter nonsense
there is no such thing as a caste system
these four
categories
and do into which society was divided
do you think india society which is more
than ten thousand years old is so
simplistic that there will be four
divisions
it's nonsense it is something the
british created
and it has become ossified it has become
set in stone because after independence
we are categorizing the government is
forcing people
to choose one of forecasts in their
birth certificates in their employment
in everything and that's why now we feel
that it is it has existed forever
india's society had the varnajati system
which is way more complicated and way
more fluid
than any four tier caste system
so it is something unfortunately it is
just deep into everyone's minds and this
question i get every single day
and i'm gonna keep telling you what the
truth is there is no such thing as a
caste system there is the varnajati
system which is a very ancient and very
complex system the british could not
understand it and that's why they
created these four divisions
in which we today categorize ourselves
and of course they they had destroyed
india's society and therefore they had
to find somebody to blame and therefore
they blamed the brahmins and they blamed
hinduism and they blamed the victims
for being victims when actually they
were the ones who had created this
entire situation so that's in brief
about it i will eventually make a
detailed video about this topic because
it's not something that can be addressed
in five minutes
all right
lots of questions i can see now
chandranch
please tell us the story of chanakya
it's a confusion some say that chanakya
defeated alexander the tyrant but after
seeing my thoughts it doesn't look like
that
vishnu gupta chanakya was the mentor of
chandragupta maurya
now there is a bit of confusion whether
it was chandragupta maurya who was the
emperor of india when alexander invaded
or was it his predecessors and the
nandas
so there is a bit of confusion as you
know india's history is quite vague and
it
there is a lot of confusion now
chanakya did not go to war
he was not a warrior he was the mentor
of the emperor he is the guy who trained
the emperor chandragupta maurya
so uh
according to the greek
narrative or account of events it was
alexander who fought alexander had to
fight somebody called porus they called
him porus it is probably somebody called
purushottam
who was a minor king in the western
outskirts of india
and the greeks say that alexander
defeated poros in this great battle
which was a cataclysmic
gigantic battle what actually seems to
have happened is that he that alexander
the greek lost to stem to some small
indian chieftain
on the western
fringes of india
so
it's so whatever happened whether
alexander lost or he won it is very
clear that he never actually
fought
the armies
of india's emperor he never fought
demorian forces he just fought some
small
minor
king or chieftain in western india
and most likely he lost this battle and
he was injured and he died
once he
retreated limped back to babylon
so there was no conflict as such between
the mauryans
or the nandas and alexander
so that's what most likely happened
chanakya never even
got to see the greeks
though i mean at least
when alexander attempted invading india
okay next question
is it true that extraterrestrials are
working with the us secretly well
well they haven't told me about it
so how do i answer this question
listen we have no evidence that
extraterrestrials exist
we do
see reports from time to time but those
reports are uncorroborated reports those
are not proven
some black and white hazy grainy
photographs or video footage does not
constitute proof
of the existence of extraterrestrials
so we don't know if it is true as far as
we know we don't have proof of the
existence of extraterrestrials but well
it is not impossible that it may be
happening maybe maybe but we don't have
proof we don't have evidence
okay
i have spoken a lot about afghanistan so
let's talk about something else
what else do we have
rishikesh says in what verna do farmers
come under
well
what verna is that i'm not quite very
sure they are certainly not brahmins or
and they are certainly not warriors so i
think they would
are they are the merchants what are they
i'm not very sure
i
do not want to assign
the wrong category to farmers so i'll
so i will desist from answering this
question because i am not 100 sure
sujoy asks who was sandra kottos really
chandragupta maurya or chandragupta
first of imperial gupta or mudra gupta
what are the evidences to support it i
read it i read about this from india
facts so there is a bit of confusion
there is there is a bit of uncertainty
as to who sandro cottos was
so the greeks under alexander or was it
under seleucus nicaragua most likely it
was under seleucus nicaragua they
referred to
india's ambassador as sandra kottos
so it most most likely
refers to someone called chandragupta
because the greeks were of course
mlechas they were barbarians they did
not know how to pronounce
pronounced sankhit names properly
so they called
our emperor sandra kothos it is most
likely chandragupta maurya but there is
some confusion there is some confusion
so i haven't read the india facts
article
so i am not 100 sure as to what is
written in that article
it most likely is not samudra gupta
because samudragupta does not sound like
sandra kottos
sandra kottos most likely refers to
somebody whose name was chandragupta
so
it
seems that the most likely candidate for
this is chandragupta maurya
so that's what i'll go with as of right
now
all right what else do we have
donggar singh johann says you said many
times that partition was useless but
don't you think that if india pakistan
were a single boundary or single entity
then there would be daily riots and our
demographics would be more muslim
majority by now
see
it's like this
india was partitioned because india's
leaders
were feeble
they were incapable we had nehru and
gandhi
right those are weak leaders those are
those are incompetent leaders and that's
why india was partitioned
india would not have been partitioned if
india had a strong iron build leader
somebody like subhash chandra bose now
imagine we have someone like subhashan
rabos who has
ensured there is no partition do you
imagine that someone like subhashin
rabus would allow daily riots to happen
i mean are you serious sir
someone like subhashandrabose or someone
of that caliber
would never
tolerate
any rioting
or any religious strife they would put
it down with an iron fist
so had india not been partitioned
india would have had a very strong
leadership
and under a strong leadership such
things simply don't happen
the problem is that we have only seen
weak leadership in the past 70 years so
we indians can't imagine what a strong
leader looks like
we have only seen weak leaders we have
only seen appeasement
we have only seen vote bank politics and
we have only seen this religious
this hindu muslim nonsense
that's all we have seen and therefore we
imagine that the only thing that would
have happened if there was no partition
was daily riots
no sir absolutely not under a strong
leadership
there would have been no rioting and
there would have been none of this
nonsense that we see every day so that's
my answer
all right some more questions
what's my what are my views about dev
that partner listen i do not have any
views about individuals i do not discuss
individuals unless those are historical
figures or those are individuals that
truly matter do i discuss individuals do
i discuss audrey trishky or david
do i discuss myself
we don't matter we just regular
individuals i will discuss individuals
who are historical figures
or world leaders who is this devoted
pertinent he's nobody i don't discuss
people like that it's pointless please
understand this it is pointless
disgusting people
discuss something bigger than that
okay rajesh asks in what ways is
communism affecting nepal love from
nepal love back to nepal you are our
brothers and sisters great to hear from
you
so in what ways is communism affecting
nepal well well the major political
ideology right now in nepal seems to be
communism
uh it all
originates
in the policies of the congress party
especially what's his name
rajiv gandhi
prime minister rajiv gandhi
stamped out the monarchy from nepal
he
i think it's been well documented by one
of the former
raw chiefs that uh it was all done
on the behest of the congress party and
the indian prime minister
the
hindu monarchy was destabilized and
eventually wiped out and
communism
was put in its place as a replacement
ideology
so
today i think
the major political parties espouse
communism and they are very much under
the sway of the chinese communist party
and hinduism is on very shaky ground in
nepal
you have
widespread conversions to christianity
that are going on ever since the
earthquake happened
right a few years ago
so that's what's happening in nepal
right now communism is very
very much powerful
and the chinese communist party seems to
have a great deal of control
on various political matters in nepal so
that's
where we stand today which is very
disappointing very unfortunate that this
beautiful
very cultured nation
is currently in this sort of situation
so one would like to see that change
it's gonna take some time
right
interpol asks what is putin's political
ideology is he orthodox christian
traditionalist or marxist and why does
he support arab arab regimes
i think putin's
political ideology is
nationalism that's what it is
he wants to rebuild
russia he wants to make russia strong
again
and
he does
he's definitely not marxist
he did uh
he did get all his training under the
kgb under the ussr so maybe he
wants to recreate that sort of power
structure to some extent
but i don't think he's a marxist
he may be
a bit of
several things at once but the main
thing is he's an is a nationalist he's a
russian nationalist and he wants to see
russia strong again like it was during
the days of the ussr
now why does he support arab regimes he
will support whoever it takes to further
his national interest i have explained
the national interest i have explained
geopolitics
it doesn't matter whom you support as
long as they
give you what you require
every country looks at the world through
the prism of its own
national interest its long-term national
interest and if it is worthwhile to ally
yourself with an arab country or a
dictatorship or something else you do it
there is no right or wrong there is no
good or bad there is no black or white
you have to your job as the ruler
is to serve your country and its people
that's all your job is
and there is no right or wrong in that
so that's why he does it because it
makes sense
okay some more questions
danandre asks
why are indians not able to win nobel
prizes in science
well there are a number of reasons for
that first of all the nobel prizes are
biased and there goes my chance
look the nobel prizes are
known to be biased
it has been well documented i've got a
book somewhere here it's called a
beautiful mind by sylvia nasser in which
she has
demonstrated what kind of backroom
politics happens
during
the time that a nobel prize winner is
being chosen so nobel prizes are biased
have you heard of dr subramanyam now
what's his name
dr
ecg sudharshan
george the sudarshan he should have won
a nobel prize in physics three times
and every time
somebody else was given the nobel prize
for work that sudharshan had done
so it's well known and many many
physicists even wrote
letters to the nobel prize committee
protesting against this treatment
so there is definitely a great deal of
bias first of all
in awarding the nobel prizes
and secondly
it is also true that india's uh
india doesn't
uh
invest a great deal in
furthering
science i mean india's universities are
are
terrible
the research atmosphere is non-existent
india's professors
well they don't really do any research
they take a textbook and they will read
it out to you or they will write stuff
from the textbook onto the blackboard
and that's it that job is done they
don't really do any real research there
are i'm not saying there is no research
there are some brilliant scientists in
india
professors
but that's like one in a hundred
the overwhelming majority of professors
in india because of the system are such
that they don't do any research the
system is like this it promotes
mediocrity and destroys talent if you
want to advance in indian academia
in the indian academic system then you
have to be good at politics
if you're good at research they're going
to suppress you if you're good at
politics and climbing the ladder and so
on then you will
advance in the system
and therefore the people who advance the
most are the ones who are the best
politicians not the best scientists
so because of this sort of system
you don't get good science happening in
india
everybody tries to leave india
and that's why all india's scientists
are working abroad
i mean those who could get out and those
who are still in india are unfortunately
not not able to do any genuine research
so that's another reason why india
does not really win nobel prizes in
the sciences
okay
what else
do we have
chaitanya says why does telugu sound
more like sanskrit than hindi i think
the
amount of sanskrit content in the telugu
language is more than in hindi hindi is
a badly contaminated language it has a
great deal of persian and arabic words
now i know what you will say that
portion itself is descended from
sanskrit but persian itself
is a badly contaminated language it has
a lot of loan words from arabic and god
knows where else
so that's why hindi sounds more like
urdu there are turkic words there are
persian words there are arabic words in
hindi
lots of them
so it sounds more like a foreign
language at times but telugu has a great
deal of sanskrit i would say
at least 50 or 16 percent of the
vocabulary in telugu comes from sanskrit
and you could say something similar
about kannada as well
and even about malayalam
and about tamil so these languages in
southern india sound more like sanskrit
than hindi does isn't that strange and
isn't that disappointing
but that's just how it is
okay some more questions
where where else do we go
swastika says
do you think economic developments and
scientific innovations
will bring back our lost knowledge
culture
and sanatan dharma back to power
economic developments and scientific
innovations
make
a country
or a society stronger more powerful more
prosperous
so that brings power back to a society
see in the past 1000 years we have lost
we have lost control of our geography
it has been controlled by outsiders and
they have been eroding our culture and
our dharma sanatan dharma right that's
what they've been doing they have
destroyed all of our universities
they've burned all our libraries we have
lost a great deal of knowledge
so now today india is taking baby steps
back
at regaining its lost position on the
global stage
which takes a lot of economic work and
scientific innovations
so as our economy grows stronger and as
hopefully we rediscover our great
aptitude for science and technology
as we do that in the next few decades
maybe in the next 50 years or 100 years
india will rise again as a great power
it is inevitable as long as we have the
right leadership
but the knowledge that we lost all the
books all the millions of books that
were burnt
in the great fires of our libraries
those will not come back
those
some of that knowledge much of that
knowledge is lost forever
so what needs to happen is we need to
we need to create new knowledge
we need to create knowledge
based on what we know we have lost
and we need to create new knowledge
based on science and technology
so it is pointless to to cry about
spilled milk
it's happened
we have to remember what happened and we
have to ensure it never happens again
learn the lessons of history but the
knowledge that is burned is burned now
we need to what we can do is we can
recreate the institutions based on our
culture and our values
our civilizational values
we can recreate a new
education system
based on our traditional civilizational
values
based on the old patterns not based on
the western system which doesn't really
work
and after doing that we can start
creating new knowledge new scientific
discoveries new philosophical
discoveries and all that and that is
what is going to
uh
hopefully trigger off a renaissance in
our culture in civilization so that is
what we can do
but what is lost
may not be
possible to
revive
so that is where we stand today
certain things are just gone
but we have to move on we have to move
forward
and we have to
find ways
of respecting our ancestors and our lost
knowledge
that's what i would say
okay more questions
okay look at let's take a look at this
if a black hole eats the earth
or our solar system can we survive it
or are there any ways that we can
prevent a black hole from approaching us
if a black hole eats the earth there is
absolutely no way we can survive it
or even the solar system a black hole
that would eat the solar system would
need to be very very large
so there's no way we can survive such an
event because this is a force of nature
uh
is there any way we can prevent a black
hole from approaching us as of today no
we would not even be able to see a black
hole because it's dark
it's not black it's just dark it's
transparent maybe we could see the
gravitational lensing that happens
around it
but that's only if we get very very very
lucky
so as of today
there's no way we can survive an event
like this and there's no way we can
prevent a black hole from approaching us
we simply do not have the technological
know-how to do that
but of course it's never happened in the
past three and a half four billion years
so
there's a good chance it won't happen in
the next few billion years
so that's all we can do about it
pranay says is it possible that human
species evolved separately in india
because india was part of africa
and we can see similarities between the
animal species that are found in india
and africa
see india was part of africa about 60 70
or something million years ago
humanity is about 2 million years old
when humanity first evolved
our distant ancestors at that time india
was already part of asia understand the
chronology who's the politician of
chronology summa j
understand the chronology understand the
time scales we're talking about
right so when india was part of africa
no humans existed dinosaurs were still
everywhere
even those that died out
in the great event of 65 million years
ago
so
there is no evidence that human species
evolved separately in india
if we find such evidence then we can
take that seriously but as of today
no
there is no such evidence and therefore
to the best knowledge that we have
the best evidence that we have it tells
us that that humanity first
emerged in africa if we find better
evidence
elsewhere then i will change my opinion
as of today
from the best evidence i have seen
i can say
that it is quite likely
that humanity
originated in africa
all right let's see some more questions
uh divia says why can't india use its
soft power like south korea is using
k-pop and its entertainment industry
well it is not it is doing so
organically it is not doing it as an
instrument of foreign policy uh the
south korean government did not create
these k-pop bands they just emerged
because south korea's society has become
prosperous enough when there is a
certain degree of prosperity
then
all these entertainment industries and
all they they just take off on their own
so uh these k-pop bands etc
emerged spontaneously organically
and somehow they seem to be
quite popular especially among teenagers
and youngsters and that's why it is
something that
kind of helps south of us south korea's
image globally
now
india does have its own entertainment
industry which is bollywood and whatnot
which is utter garbage
and bollywood has its own
agenda
of promoting of research certain flavors
of culture and all that
so it is not
working out very well it is quite
counterproductive to
india's overall image because it it it
puts forth a distorted skewed and
incorrect
image of india's culture what
westerners think of
think of india's culture
is very much influenced by bollywood and
we know that is not indian culture
so that is the reason why india is
unable to uh
to count on bollywood to a great extent
for its soft power the thing is as
india's economy slowly gets better as
india becomes more prosperous
then
such bands and music bands and all that
will emerge spontaneously across the
country india will no longer be
dependent on one city mumbai and the
small little
cabal
of bollywood entertainers for
entertainment and that's when you will
see the real flowering of indian culture
and that's when
india
will be able to
draw on that for its soft power
but i like i have mentioned in the past
soft power in itself is useless unless
you also have hard power
soft power is something that augments
hard power but it is pointless on its
own
so people don't respect a country based
on soft power people respect countries
that are prosperous and powerful and
that comes from economic power and
military power which are both forms of
hard power
so you may have the best culture but if
you are poor
and if you are weak
nobody will respect you so respect comes
from strength and only then
is soft power something that becomes
relevant
sharda says what is the future of the
of the quad after the aukus can we trust
the usa
the quad has its own place like i
explained some time ago
the quad will continue
the quad will
go on furthering its function and its
agenda
can we trust the usc certainly we can
trust the us
we can trust the us to pursue its own
national interest as long as we
understand what the american national
interest is
we know what they will do and if we know
what they will do then we can trust them
it's only when you blindly trust
somebody that you get into trouble
so india should have should be under no
illusions
india should be under no qualms india
should know exactly what america wants
in the next 10 20 years and that you can
do
if you examine
the global
geopolitical
situation and scenario
in detail
so yes
as long as we know what the usa wants we
can trust it
it is certainly not
india's friend
it is nobody's friend
it is not even australia's friend of the
uk's friend or
anybody else's friend the usa no country
has any real friends it's only temporary
alliances
as long as we understand this we are
fine
okay some more questions
can india bring back the kohinoor
diamond from the uk
maybe someday we can bring it back when
we are able to
apply the right kind of pressure and
leverage on the
on the british right now they are
sitting pretty with the diamonds and
everything else they have stolen from
india
in the future it will be possible that
india is powerful enough
as of today india is not powerful enough
sithu venkat says
is uh mr modi good leader my views on it
see in the future in the past i have
been quite critical of the government of
india
the fact is that you should never be
you should never praise the government
and your leaders too much because it
makes them complacent
i have been
quite critical on occasions of the
government of india now here's what i
have to say about mr modi i think he is
the best leader we could have asked for
today
he is a very intelligent person he knows
what he is doing
mr modi understands the world
much better than we understand it
there are things
he knows that we don't know about
he knows the global geopolitical
scenario and everything else
far better than us far better than me
and he is doing a very good job of
navigating
india through a very difficult and
dangerous time
and
most often the greatest danger you face
is not from your enemies it is from your
allies and those you consider to be your
friends
the most dangerous
people are actually the ones who are
supposedly on your side
there are certain very dangerous nations
on whose side
india
currently is
and
so that's the reason why it is a very
difficult and dangerous time it is a it
is a decade of great amount of upheaval
and
we know that mr modi
talks about vasudeva kutambakam
and he praises mohandas gandhi etc there
are reasons why he does it
there are reason there are things that
need to be done
it is not something that
many people like
i think we all agree that mr gandhi was
not the greatest of leaders
he was a hypocrite he was a british
agent and yet mr modi
praises him there is a reason for that
so i think that mr modi is
one of the best prime ministers india
has ever had i don't want to praise
anybody too much
one can praise them after they retire
but i think he's doing a very good job i
think we could not have asked for a
better leader right now and it is a very
difficult time
and we would like india to become a
superpower next week but that's not how
it works it is a long process
it's a process that has that has to be
taken up step by step by step
and
i think that's what's being done
there are many things that we are not
aware of so
so we should
not criticize too much we need to have a
little bit of patience
be patient for the next 20 years that's
what i would say
all right next question
shubham says india would be democratic
would india have been a democratic
country under nitaji
i don't know maybe india would have been
an autocratic dictatorship under
sebastian raboson is that a bad thing
i mean
even if subhashan rabos would have been
a dictator i think india
i think he had
expressed the desire to put india under
a dictatorship of of sorts for about
two decades because that's what the
country needed to kickstart its economy
and all that
and if you look at other examples take
south korea for instance south korea was
ruined
in the korean war
and it was under a dictatorship for
a significant period of time after the
korean war and that's what kickstarted
its economy if you look at the story of
vietnam or if you look at certain other
countries you see similar patterns
so maybe it would have been a good thing
to have
a one-man one-party kind of rule for 20
years or so
and use that to kick start india's
economy because as we know democracy it
works only when a country is really
prosperous
when a country is not prosperous when a
country has lots of problems in
democracy it does more harm than it does
good especially a fake democracy like
like the one we have in india in which
you are only allowed to vote once in
five years but you cannot really
participate in governance
and you don't have any democracy
any internal democracy within political
parties in india so this is a fake
democracy it's a pretend democracy i
think a dictatorship may have been a
good idea as long as it was under
somebody who really meant well somebody
like subhash and rabos maybe it would
have been a good thing maybe who knows
it's only speculation
okay what else do we have
preet says why is our government
changing the education system
i think there is uh
some new education policy or something
which does some kind of
which uh seeks to change the education
system to some extent i think it is not
enough why are we changing it because
the education system is something that
still
lives in the 19th century it is a
colonial artifact
it does not
see the the what is the purpose of an
education system the purpose of the
education system is to empower
the student
it is to give the student the best
possible tools
for success in life
and if you empower the student
and
create
these
confident
capable talented
young
citizens who could be future leaders
then it's good for the country now the
indian education system does not do that
it's simply it is designed to mass
produce clerks and peons
and coolies
it mentally brainwashes students and
it does the very opposite thing
then it's supposed to do it does not
give you any confidence it robs you of
your confidence so these are the reasons
why there is a need to reform the
education system now
the government has
unveiled this new education policy that
seeks to do some such thing
i think it's not enough but at least
they're doing something
so there is a reason why the government
is changing the education system
rishikesh says do we really need this
very complex legislative
system no we don't need a very complex
education legislative system the system
that we have the system of governance
the system of legislation
these two houses of parliament and then
you have all these little space state
assemblies that go on and on god knows
what they do
it is a very complex and cumbersome
system you have so many elections every
year it's a never-ending process the
entire energy of the country is wasted
within
instead of being focused on developing
the country we don't need this
it is
a system that was
built by anglophiles
it was built by our so-called leaders
who were so much in love with the
british that even after the british left
they wanted a system that reminded that
reminded them of the british
and this system is something that
developed
in
england
in the past 1000 years
this westminster system of democracy
parliament democracy it is suited for a
small island it is not suited for a
subcontinent-sized
civilization such as india so it is
not
what this country needs it is something
that is counter productive
to the national interest
hari says is it possible for two
galaxies to collide with each other then
what happens
yes galaxies do collide or rather they
merge together
so galaxies are enormous collections of
stars
our own galaxy has hundreds of millions
of stars
so when two galaxies come together under
the influence of gravity of their mutual
gravity then what happens is that they
essentially merge together there is no
actual collision because there are so
many
empty spaces between stars in the galaxy
in each galaxy
so there is a gravitational dance a
tango the gravity the the galaxies move
around each other for several billion
years eventually they merge into a
single galaxy and
there usually is a supermassive black
hole at the center of each galaxy so
these two also
go around each other and eventually
these two also seem to merge even though
there is the problem of the
there are certain problems theoretically
it seems that it should not happen but
it still does happen so that's and
that's one of the unsolved
problems in astrophysics but yes
galaxies do merge our own galaxy is
going to merge with our neighboring
galaxy which is the andromeda galaxy in
about two and a half
million
years or so
or is it billion something like that so
it's going to happen eventually
my friend brags about being a history
master what do i do in that case praise
him praise him yes sir you are a great
history master good for you what else
can i say
okay what else do we have
utsav says is it possible it was an
alien invasion theory instead of rn
invasion theory as in our hindu texts it
is said that vishnu came from vishnu
loka and similars
i don't know
as far as i know there has been no alien
invasion or aryan invasion
vishnu came from vishnu loka etc well
see look this is all philosophy and
spirituality
so we have to treat it as such
we should not take
all of these things
very literally
because there is a great deal of
metaphor in india's spiritual texts
so
that's all i have to say about that
haven't i answered this question anyway
vibor asks what's the truth behind
pratura chauhan's death we are told that
he killed gory with the help of his
friend
chand bardai that is nonsense
he was defeated in the battle
and uh
he was blinded and taken in chains
to ghazni where he was executed that's
what happened to him
abhishek says what was the khilafat
movement okay
so the khilafat movement was the
movement to
maintain the caliphate
so there have been a number of
caliphates of islam the last caliphate
was the ottoman caliphate
its uh
capital city was constantinople istanbul
and the turkish sultan was also the
caliph of the muslims which is the
religious leader of all the muslims in
the world
so in the
1900s the turkish leader mustafa kamal
ataturk
decided to abolish
the position of the caliph and he wanted
to
create a republic out of turkey
so he made the position of the caliph
quite weak and ineffectual it was clear
that he was going to abolish the
caliphate i think it was in 1918 or
there abouts
and in response to this
muslims in india certain muslim leaders
in india
started protesting against
this possibility of the abolition of the
caliphate so that was the khilafat
movement and this was a fringe movement
in india no one cared about it until
mohandas gandhi decided to support it
and then overnight it went from a fringe
movement to a national mainstream
movement
so
mr gandhi ensured that millions of
people in india supported the khilafat
moment most indians i think at the time
thought that khilafat means some kind of
protest against the british
they did not realize that they were
protesting in favor of the caliphate and
the sharia law
so that was the kill after movement
eventually the caliphate was abolished
by mustafa kamala turk and this entire
thing fizzled out
but its effect the effect of mohandas
gandhi's support for this movement
was
a pan-islamic consolidation across india
which eventually resulted in the
partition of india so that was the
killer
moment
okay do we have some more questions
rajesh says where did the white people
originate
well all people originated in africa in
the last out of africa migration which
was about 70 or 75 000 years before
today
uh originally all people were dark
skinned but there was a genetic mutation
that took place somewhere in india or
between india and the middle east and
this was the mutation for
fair skin
so this mutation first originated most
likely in india it was about some 8 000
or so years ago
and that is the origin of the white skin
so this
genetic mutation is found in india it's
found more in europe
and
so that is the origin of
white people in very brief
i think i have spoken about this in one
of my previous
live streams about the rn invasion
theory i think so i think there is a
short clip also on my channel you can
look it up
so that's the origin of white skin and
white people
okay let me take one more question for
today
madhav says i think russia is a better
ally than the us
for india what's my take on it i think
russia has
i think culturally russia is closer to
us
and india and russia understand each
other very well because of our past
experience during the cold war
as of today russia is more aligned
towards china there is a de facto
temporary alliance with china and russia
and that's why it is
important for india to keep its options
open and look for alliances everywhere
it can find this is a multilateral world
we are living in india has good
relationships with the
arabic countries india has excellent
relationships with
several european countries especially
france
india has a good working relationship
with the americans as well the americans
need india
to counter balance china
and india has an excellent relationship
with russia as well
in the past and right now also it's a
good relationship because the russians
too are quite very of china
they know that china is a big problem
even for them in the long term
so it's a complex situation i think
india and russia will always have a good
relationship
especially as china rises further
and if the americans do decline if
america does decline if the west
does decline as it is currently
declining then in the next 20 30 years
china will become more powerful in which
case india and russia will be naturally
drawn towards each other in in alliance
so it's a complex situation that we are
in right now and things are changing
quite rapidly in this decade
gaurav says does india have any space
telescope like hubble james webb
etcetera because i don't see any picture
or video from his hotel now india does
not have any
uh such any comparable
space telescope i think there is a a
mission being planned sometime in the
future maybe sometime in this decade
of some kind of space telescope
you know
creating a telescope like the building a
telescope like that and launching it
costs a great deal of money and india
seems to have decided that
the money is better used elsewhere
india does have the capability to to
build a good telescope and deploy it in
space
but as of today india does not have it i
mean we have
this spacecraft chandrayaan in orbit
around the moon but we don't see any
images being being released from it i
don't know why
i mean if you release images from the
chandrayaan spacecraft then it's going
to
uh
it's going to
make youngsters more excited about
science isn't it but still it doesn't
happen and we also have the mangalyan
spacecraft in orbit around them
around mars
from which again we don't see any
newspaper new photographs being released
so it's i don't understand this policy
of not releasing any photographs or
images of video
even though we have
the
machines in place to do that
these spacecraft do have telescopes and
other
remote sensing equipment and yet we're
not releasing it it's just a question of
i don't know either they don't have the
permission to release these images or
they just don't care i'm not sure what
it is
i think scientists would very much like
to release
new photographs and images because it's
fun isn't it
anyhow that's where we are today
okay let me take one
final question for today
aditya says i think india has i think
the us has left weapons in afghanistan
for india to control
well is india controlling any of those
weapons no
so unfortunately it is not the case
okay what else do we have what else we
have
chirinjit says india has a space
telescope named astrosat well i am not
aware of it if it is there then it's not
really really doing much
so
that's where we are
let me
take one more question
hari says why prithviraj johan remains
buried on the outskirts of the afghan
city of ghazni
i've heard the story too but i don't
know how true it is i've heard the story
that he's buried somewhere out there
well if he is buried there it's because
they chose to bury him there
what can i say there is
uh this hasn't been confirmed by
archaeologists
but i have heard this story several
times so
that's what it is
okay one final question for today
okay this is today's last question we
have such good relations with japan
why doesn't the indian government work
together
and find the reality of the ashes of
netaji kept in the renkoji temple for
dna test
listen
you cannot dna test ashes
when you burn a body
everything gets burned including dna
there is no dna test of ashes you just
can't do it you will not find a single
strand of dna in ashes and that's why
it's pointless to try and do dna test
of those ashes most likely the indian
government knows what happened to nitaj
subhash and rabos most likely it is
it is most likely that it was that
netaji did not die in that so-called
plane crash
most likely gubnami baba was netaji
it still remains to be proven but it
seems to be very likely
so the indian government
i think knows what the truth is it has
simply not it has simply not released
that information to the public thus far
and that is why
that i think is why it is not bothering
about those ashes kept in the renkoji
temple
so that's where we are
all right my friends i'm gonna stop it
right here
thank you very much for all your
questions it was great to see you all
again today
and i will see you in tomorrow's live
session live stream which is going to be
in hindi the first hindi live stream so
i will see you
tomorrow
in hindi same time
on my hindi channel
until then
thank you very much
for your viewership i appreciate it very
much thank you very much have a good day
have a good night and i will see you
soon
bye